<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true impartiall narration, concerning the armies preservation of the King; by which it doth appear, that the army doth intend the good, life, propertie, and libertie of all the commons of England.</title>
            <author>Joyce, George, fl. 1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87388</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862086</idno>
  <idno type="VID">114235</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240906973</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E393_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201587</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862086</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862086e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87388)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E393[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true impartiall narration, concerning the armies preservation of the King; by which it doth appear, that the army doth intend the good, life, propertie, and libertie of all the commons of England.</title>
                  <author>Joyce, George, fl. 1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Joyce by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 17th 1647".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:114235:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114235:1"/>
            <head>A true impartiall Narration, concerning the Armies preservation of the <hi>KING;</hi> by which it doth appear, that the Army doth intend the Good, Life, Propertie, and Libertie of all the Commons of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FEllow Commoners, considering with our selves how variously those men will report, that endeavour to carry on their designs, though it be to the ruine &amp; the destruction of others, who are their Fellow-Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and have as just a right and propriety to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and freedoms of the Nation as themselves: And consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering also how misinformation may seduce you, and draw you away from the knowing of things in their true unmixt nature, and consequently from acting and walking accordingly; so that not onely our selves may be drawn by such misrepresentations of things into unexpressible extraordinary sadnesses, miseries, and calamities, but also you, into perpetuall irrecoverable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude and bondage, even in a moment of time, before you, or we are aware of: And also considering that certain of the House of Commons have sold the record of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> (which doth demonstrate the Subjects rights, liberties and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114235:2"/>for 10000 l. so that it might never be used again, as we can (we hope) evidently prove; so that by it you may see their designe. Therefore, we (who have fought for you in the sight of the Sun, and for your liberties and proprieties, as well as our own; and have been faithfull to you in the apprehensions of all rationall men, and those that will not lie against their own souls, or walk contrary to the Testimony of their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences) cannot choose but with reciprocall tendernesse pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent unto you truely, briefly, and clearly, without partiality the nature of the businesse concerning the Kings Majesty, and us at <hi>Holdenby, June</hi> the 4. 1647.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday, Coronet <hi>Joyce</hi> went to the bowling-green, where his Majesty was at bowls within a mile of <hi>Holdenby;</hi> the cause of the Coronets being there, was to prevent the Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conveyed away in a secret manner, which was justly suspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, to be done by some that were with his Majesty. Coronet <hi>Joyce,</hi> an appointed agent by the Army, observing a sudden al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in perswading the King to go to my Lord Spencers to bowls, when the King had resolved before to go two miles fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and at the Kings taking horse, Colonell <hi>Graves,</hi> and a Scottish Lord whispered, and were more then ordinary earnest in their privacy, which did occasion jealousie at that opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. After the King had been at bowls one hour, <hi>Graves</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned a Souldier, and asked him from whence he came; The Souldiers answer was, from <hi>Oxford,</hi> and that he had been late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Army: Then <hi>Graves</hi> asked, if the Army was not contented with the Ordinance of Indempnitie, and the Votes of Parliament? the Souldier answered, No, and that it would in no way secure them; and gave <hi>Graves</hi> a reason, because many of their fellow Souldiers, and those that had acted for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were molested notwithstanding it: and what a sad thing will it be to consider, that the Souldiery shall taste of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Judges cruelty, notwithstanding their good services,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114235:2"/>and the preserving of the heads of some men in the Parliament. And therefore judge how much below the light of nature these men live, and how much they exercise themselves in tyranny, when they will not do good unto those that do good unto them. Then <hi>Graves</hi> asked him more news, and said, he need not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; But he said, He was not afraid of him, or any man in the Kingdom, for he had done nothing that he knew of to make him afraid; and he further said, He would dead ingeniously with him, and tell him the truth of any thing he should ask him. The <hi>Graves</hi> asked, if he did not hear of a party of horse; he answered, he did more then hear of a party, for he saw them the day before within thirty miles of <hi>Holdenby:</hi> this made <hi>Graves</hi> tremble as if he had been guilty of something he had done or intended to do, otherwise why should he afterwards, and the Scottish Lord his confederate have run away, when no man intended to do them the least hurt in the world. But the Scottish Lord went to <hi>London,</hi> and hath notoriously wronged the King, and the party also that did secure his Majesties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for the peace and safety of the Kingdom, as was declared at large before a thousand witnesses: so that by it you may see the designe of a cunning <hi>Scot,</hi> and what such will do to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and honour, even against King and People.</p>
            <p>Further, for the security of the Kings Person, the party marched toward. <hi>Holdenby,</hi> and when they came to the house, the Commissioners sent one Captain <hi>Middleton</hi> to know of us what we came for and what we would have, and who command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Answer was made him, All did command, and ye were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der command. Then Captain <hi>Middleton</hi> replyed, If you have any thing to do here, the Commissioners would know what it is, and desired that they would send in to the Commissioners, one or more, to certifie what was the intent of coming thither.</p>
            <p>Whereupon Coronet <hi>Joyte,</hi> by unanimous consent of the party, went in to the Commissioners, and told them the truth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114235:3"/>of their coming thither, which was to secure his Majesties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and to protect them, there being a secret designe as they were informed, to convey or steal away the King, and to raise another Army to suppresse this under his Excellency Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fairfax:</hi> Likewise, he said, he knew no other way to keep this Kingdom from blood, or another war, but by the present security of the Kings Person, and that he may be no more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and if he were, that the Kingdom were utterly undone for ever: If this be all, said the Commissioners, it is well done.</p>
            <p>But after it, Coronet <hi>Joyce</hi> spake more to the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and told them, He did humbly conceive, that there were some who did delay Justice, and seek onely to disband the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who were raised for the defence of the just rights, proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and liberties of the Subject, and the bringing of all unjust men to condigne punishment; such who did endeavour to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the fundamentall Laws of the Kingdom: and he said, He did beleeve that there were some who did endeavour to pull down King and People, and to set up themselves, and who they were, the Commissioners and the world may judge and see by their actions.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he took his leave of the Commissioners for a while, lest the King should be disturbed in his Bed-chamber. Then Major-Generall <hi>Brown</hi> went to the King, &amp; did assure his Majesty of the truth of the businesse, &amp; desired his Majesty not to be troubled, for no hurt would come unto him, for they were all civill Gentlemen, and that his Majesty should find it so. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this was done, the Coroner went to the Commissioners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and desired them to give him Orders, he being willing to obey them, because they were appointed by the Parliament to be there to that end: Then Major-Generall <hi>Brown</hi> said, Come again by and by and we will give you Orders, in the mean time set your Guard, and place your Sentinels, which directions of his we followed, &amp; told him and the rest of the Commissioners
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114235:3"/>if they would give us orders I would obey them, provided they were just, and for the security of the Kings person. All this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done it grew towards noon: After that, Coronet <hi>Joyce</hi> desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Souldiers to mount to horse, and told them they should all go to quarters; at which word of command all was done, &amp; the said Coronet was to give in a relation to the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his coming, and the grounds in writing, and did; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the multiplicity of businesse, could not give it in that form as otherwise he might if he had had time.</p>
            <p>All this being done, all was quiet in the said present security of his Majesty, untill tidings came that <hi>Graves</hi> was gone quite away, and thereupon it was supposed he was (and thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self also) guilty, or else he would have stayed; but none could tell what was become of him: and some of his damming blades did say and swear, they would fetch a party, which party could not be from the Army, but must be from some other place; and therefore to prevent disturbance and blood, and for the peace sake of the Kingdome, all declared unanimously, that they thought it most convenient to secure the King in another place, from such persons as should cunningly or desperately take him away contrary to order, which was endeavoured ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry earnestly (as we are informed) by some that are enemies to the peace of the Kingdome, and the prosperity of the Army</p>
            <p>But another cause of jealousie was, not knowing the resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of those who quartered Souldiers, and pretended for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, to give all satisfaction to the whole Kingdome, and to the reall effecting of a businesse of such concernment, the Souldiers sent Coronet <hi>Joyce</hi> to the Commissioners at ten of the clock at night, who desired the Commissioners to let the King know he would speak with him; some of the Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners being unwilling, held the Coronet in discourse about half an hour, untill the King was asleep in his bed; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114235:4"/>the said Coronet could not be contented till he had spoken with the King, it being the onely way and meanes to prevent trouble for the future, and blood that might come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the Kingdome; and therefore the said Coronet judged it in his owne conscience requisite to speak with him at that opportunity, and therefore he offered the Commissioners to go with them with as much gentlenesse and tendernesse as he could, to tell his Majesty something for his and the Kingdomes good; which was to take him from thence, there being a secret designe to steal and convey away his Majesties person, to side with some who pretend justice and deceive the Kingdome, and obstruct the relief of poor distressed <hi>Ireland,</hi> intending to break the Army in peeces now under the command of Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fairfax</hi> our Generall, and to raise another Army to carry on their designe; and that all rationall men may see it by the actions of some men, (as <hi>Stapleton, Glinn, Green, Erle,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) who said, Its now come to that, that they must sinke us, or we must finke them. Much more was spoken by the said Coronet, but this in brief: I was willing to let all passe without giving a relation, untill I heard that the Scottish Lord had falsely told the Parliament of our proceedings with the King, who saw or heard it not; for he was not within a mile of the Court when all these forementioned passages were; for the Scotrish Lord as we are informed, reported, that the King was taken away against his will: For although the King told Coronet <hi>Joyce</hi> before the Commissioners, he was unwilling to goe with us; yet he said, That such reasons might be produced that might prevaile with him, and then he did protest nothing should stay him but he would goe, whether the Commissioners would yea or no. And reasons were given accordingly, which did prevail with his Majesty to promise to goe the next morning, and he gave a confirmation of his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnesse, by saying to the Coronet, He should be the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114235:7"/>to goe if the Coronet would promise him some things which he should propound: The Coronet said, He would, if they were just and warrantable in his understanding, and desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Majesty that he might hear the things. Then his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty spake before the Commissioners, and said, Master <hi>Joyce,</hi> I have this to propound unto you. May it please your Majesty, I am willing to hear, said Coronet <hi>Joyce;</hi> but am sorry I have disturbed you out of your sleep: but the King said no matter, no matter, if you mean me no hurt: and then spake, <hi>viz,</hi> if you will promise me that I shall have no hurt: saying, You may take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my life if you wil, having the sword in your hands. This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the Coronet made, That the Parliament had declared to preserve his Majesties person, and that they being the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Army, should not but endeavour the same; only they did desire to secure him from being taken away, lest he should be set at the head of another Army, and so this Kingdome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved into danger. And all this was said in answer to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie's first proposition. The second was, That he would not be forced to any thing against his conscience by us. He answered, that he would be unwilling to force any man against his conscience, much lesse his Majesty: and also said, That he hoped he was sensible of those that did endeavour to force men against their consciences,<note place="margin">Observe, none will oppose this Army, but guilty consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and they will fly in our faces or raise an Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us.</note> and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laved to doe justice or settle the Kingdome, for which they were sent; and did endeavour to disband or break this Army in pieces; who sought nothing but justice, as will appear here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to all the world: Pray God it may, said the King.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He demanded, whether yea or no he should have his servants with him, and whether he should be provided for like a man in his place, and that be had been courteously used by those Commissioners that were with him, as ever he was by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. The Cornet answered, that he should endeavour as farre as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114235:5"/>in him lay, to shew him all just and due respect: And that he might be no otherwise attended on then before, the Coronet desired the Commissioners of Parliament to go with the King &amp; discharge that trust imposed on them; &amp; the souldiery of the Army would assist them so long as they were just and honest: Then said the King, I will willingly goe along with you, if the souldiers will confirme what you have promised me; the King believing I had said nothing but what they would stand to: All this being spoken at ten or eleven at night: And when the King had done propounding of these Questions to the Coronet, he gave his word to be ready by six the next morning, to hear if the souldiers would confirm what I had promised; and if they would, he would willingly goe with us: for it was so bad an ayre that he could never be so well as he had been, and if he were once gone, he would be unwilling to come back again to that place any more; many other reasons he had which he gave not. According to his promise he came in the morning at six of the clock, where he found all the souldiers ready mounted to martch with him; but before he would martch, he desired to speak the same things to the souldiers which he spake over night to the Coronet, to see if they would confirme what he said and had promised; which they did with one consent: and before the souldiers, the King was pleased to ask the Coronet, What Commission he had to secure his person? then said the Coroner, If the Parliament had ever made an Order, that the army should not have secured the King's person, he should not have dared to doe what he had done: but he being informed his Majesty was to be conveyed away, which if not prevented, might have caused another War, and involved the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in blood againe; this was the only cause of our securing the King's person: This answer did not satisfie the King, but he asked, What commission I had for doing that I did? I told his Majesty, the souldiery of the Army, or else I should not have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114235:5"/>dared to have done what I have: and conceiving it to be the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to bring peace to England, and Justice with Mercy, which is the thing which all honest men do desire, and none will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but some guilty consciences, who by their will seek to destroy both King and people, to set up themselves. Yet the King was not satisfied with this, but asked, Whether I had nothing in writing from Sir Thomas Fairfax our General, to do what I did: the Coronet desired the King he would not ask him such Questions, for he did conceive he had sufficiently answered him before: then said the King, I pray M. Joyce deal ingenuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with me, and tell me what Commission you have. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronets answer was, Here is my Commission. Where, said the King? He answered, Here: his Majesty again asked, Where? He answered, Behind me, and desired his Majesty that that might satisfie him: whereupon the King smiled; and said, It is as fair a Commission, and as well writen as he had seen a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission written in his life. A company of handsome proper Gentle-men as he had seen a great while. But what if I should yet refuse to go with you, I hope you would not force me? I am your King, and you ought not to lay violent hands on your King: for I do acknowledge none to be above me here, but God: Then said M. Joyce, Our desires are not to force your Majesty, but have humbly intreated your Majesty to go with us; and not only your self, but the Commissioners: and to this end, that the Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners might discharge that trust imposed on them as honest members of Parliament. Then spake one of the Commissioners of Parliament and shewed us a paper, what was therein we saw not; they all spake to us in order, the last that spake, as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was Major Generall Brown; who said the Commissioners had an order of Parliament to look to the King at Holdenby; &amp; if he had strength we should have had his life before we should have brought the King away: Indeed, said the Coronet, you speak like a faithfull and gallant man, but he knew well enough
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114235:6"/>he had not strength, and therefore he spake so boldly. Major G. Grown said further, But since it is so, I must do what you will have me, being not able to resist you. Then spake Coronet Joyce further, We came not to have the bloud of any man, but for peace; and did hope should manifest it all to the world, for he sought peace with all men as much as in him ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and further he said. They were servants to the Parliament and Kingdome, and had served them faithfully ever since the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this warre: or else more heads had been cut off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time: and if the souldiers had been ordered, not to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his Majesty, they would not have dared to have done it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they were servants to the State as well as the Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; they did what they did to keep the Kingdome from bloud and a second warre, which if not prevented, might unhappily have come upon us suddenly; as you may fee is the endeavour of some men, who pretend to be the Kings, and Kingdomes best friends. After this, the King was going away, but turned and said, Now Gentlemen, for the place you intend to have me to?</p>
            <p>M. Joyce answered, If it please your Majestie to Oxford.</p>
            <p>The King replyed, That is no good aire.</p>
            <p>M. Joyce faid, Then to Cambridge.</p>
            <p>The King did not like that, but said he like New-market. It was an aire that did very well agree with him.</p>
            <p>And it was granted by M. Joyce he should go thither.</p>
            <p>Then the King asked M. Joyce, How farre he intended to ride that night?</p>
            <p>And M. Joyce answered and faid; As farre as your Majesty can conveniently ride.</p>
            <p>The King smiling said, I can ride as farre as you, or any man there: but he concluded to talk of that, and his accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation privately; and so he courteously took his leave of the company, and was going, and one whispered him, and he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114235:6"/>back, and heard the Commissioners speak to the company thus in order: First my Lord Montague spake and said Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, we are intrusted by both Houses (shewing in his hand a paper, the authority they had) and desire to know whether all the party do agree to what M. Joyce hath said.</p>
            <p>And they cryed, All, All.</p>
            <p>And he having spoke low, Sir Iohn Cook seconded him with a loud voice, and added that as the Parliament had intrusted them, had he but Forces to withstand the party, he would have done it with his life: and M. Crew said the same.</p>
            <p>And Major G. Brown spake last to the same purpose, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded something more then the rest: saying, It was not the first time that he had been in the head of a party, and that they knew not the Law: and he durst affirm that scarce two in the company, although they cryed. All, All, knew what the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had delivered to the King. And therefore he said with a loud voice, All that are willing the King shall stay with us the Commissioners of Parliament, let them speak. And all the party cryed, None, None, then said he, I have done. Onely the souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers said, we understand well enough what we do. Now let all the world judge that is done, and who is in fault, and who they are that seeke warre, and no peace not Justice.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb facs="tcp:114235:7"/>
            <head>One word more Fellow. Commoners.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends and fellow-Commoners, we the Souldiery under his Excelleney Sr Tho Fairfax do desire to speake one word to you All; that so you may see and know our very hearts so far as we know them our selves: And that our earnest desires are for Peace, in this our Native Land and Kingdome; and being more sensible then many thousands are, how destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive another Warre will be, if not our utter ruine and undoing The words we shall speak to you, are to prevent Warr, and to find out those that have of late sent that Scottish Lord who went from Holmby to London, and from thence into France, and another Scotch Lord into Scotland, all this to bring another Army to England: and we shall be able to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to you hereafter who are the chief actors therein. Deare Friends and Fellow Commoners let us not be like those who have set their hands to the plough and look back, but let it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to all the World we are against another Warre, and for Peace, Mercy and Justice without delay, No look about you and be not deluded any longer, lest the Scot sell the King for more money, and others oppresse the Kingdome, and put the Kingdomes treasure into their own pockets, or send it out of our Kingdome, as if they were preparing to go after, for feare they should be found out. This we speak that so you may have a care of this glorious Kingdome, your shipping being now in those mens hands who have done you most wrong; and if not looked after by you, may suddenly let in a forrein Enemy to overrun you all, and ravish your Wives, and rost your Children alive, as those bloudy minded men in Ireland have done; and this will be our case if you awake not suddenly. I have done, a word to the wise is sufficient: and rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours and the Kingdomes faithfull servant till death for Englands Lyberty, against Tyranny, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>